and one policy that tries to more
closely approximate LRU is the so called
pseudo LRU policy so it's really trying
to approximate LRU but sometimes it
doesn't exactly match it so let's look
at an 8 way set associative cache and
with the su bel-air your policy what we
keep is one bit per line in the set so
in an 8 way set associative cache we
will have a 1 bit associated with each
line as opposed to three bits that we
would need for LRU counters so how does
it allow you work all of the bits start
out at zero and what we will do is every
time a line is accessed we will set its
bit to one so for example this one
becomes one this one becomes one then
this one becomes one as long as there is
at least one zero bit here we keep doing
this and if you ever need to replace
something we pick among the blocks whose
bits are zero so all the recently
accessed blocks will have the bits at
one and thus be saved from replacement
eventually however if we have a lot of
hits so for example in this particular
state we will pick the least recently
used block because it's the only one
that has a zero bit
eventually however all of the bits will
be set so eventually we will have this
become one and now we cannot replace
anything so we detect this situation
where all the bits have become one and
when we set the last zero bit to one we
zero out the remaining bits so now we
have state that is similar to what not
most recently used would tell us we only
know what was the most recently used
block for the rest of them we need to
pick at random if something is to be
replaced but as we start accessing some
other blocks we get a better idea of
which ones are more and which ones are
less recently used so at any given point
in time this pseudo LRU policy is
somewhere between the NMR you and the
LRU policy we have seen that when one
bit is said we are effectively
implementing the NMR policy when more
than one bit is set
not almost all of them we are in between
and when all but one are set we are
implementing the true LRU policy because
we know exactly which one block is the
least recently used so this policy
behaves somewhere in between LRU and
anna-marie Oh in exchange for using more
bits but it's also very simple because
on a hit all we have to do is set the
bit that corresponds to the block which
can be done very quickly and efficiently
so as far as activity on a cache head is
concerned both pseudo LRU and NMR you
have much less activity than LRU which
helps us with both power and also hit
time of the cache